Guide to the Van Schaick family papers,1732-1846.
Van Schaick family papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Van Schaick family papers, 1732-1846.
393
Van Schaick family.
.2 cubic ft.
Correspondence, accounts, receipts, deeds, wills, inventory, and other papers.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, accounts, receipts, deeds (including deeds for the sale of slaves), wills, inventory, and other papers pertaining to land transactions and other activities of the van Schaick family, including Anna, Anthony, Christina, Gerrit, Jacob, John, Henry, and Gerard van Schaick. Also, a map for the village of Oswego, New York.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, accounts, receipts, deeds (including deeds for the sale of slaves), wills, inventory, and other papers pertaining to land transactions and other activities of the van Schaick family, including Anna, Anthony, Christina, Gerrit, Jacob, John, Henry, and Gerard van Schaick. Also, a map for the village of Oswego, New York.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Van Schaick family.; Van Schaick, Anna.; Van Schaick, Anthony.; Van Schaick, Christina.; Van Schaick, Gerard.; Van Schaick, Gerrit.; Van Schaick, Henry.; Van Schaick, Jacob.; Van Schaick, John.
Subjects:
Real property, Exchange of.; Slave records.
Places:
Oswego (N.Y.)--Maps.
Form and Genre Terms:
Deeds.; Inventories.; Wills.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- 1732-1748
  - 1 Deed, sale of a negro woman, about 18 - July 7, 1736 - Albany, Koenvaet Ten Eyck to Anthony van Schaick, 38 pounds. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 2 Land Deeds
    - 1735-1736 - Elisabeth van Corlaer and Anthony van Schaick, Albany Co. - 16 pounds (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1747 - John J. Schalenbeck, Cogshagkie, and Wm. van Styck and Jacob van Schaick, Albany - 40 shillings (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 5 Receipts
    - 1744, Sybrant van Scharyick to Raphael Goilet (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1745, 1747, Brandt Schuyler, Peter Schuyler, George Lieber, Rood to Jacob van Schaick. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1 Letter - 1746 - Levinius van Schaick, New York, to Charles Town, South Carolina, demanding payment of a bill. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1 Letter in Dutch - 1742 - Levinius van Schaick, N. Y. to Jacob van Schaick (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 1750-1760
  - 1 Letter in Dutch - 1753 - Theod. Vanwyck, N. Y. to Jacob van Schaick (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1 Letter to Jacob van Schaick, Albany - 1760 - from George Lieberrood, N. Y., order for goods - wishes to have goods before "river freezes" - speaks of diversity of prices (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Copy of letter to John Halnbeek, unsigned from Albany - 1755 - concerning possession of "the island" (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 5 Receipts - to Jacob van Schaick - 1754 - 1760 - from H. Gansevoort, Grant Vanhorne, George Glentworth of the Royal Hospital, Dirck ten Broeck, D. Schuyler (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1 Deed, sale of a negro woman, about 21 - July 8, 1758 - Garrit Stothoff, to Jacob van Schaick, Albany - 55 pounds (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1 Account of barrels of cider bought by Jacob van Schaick - 1757 - signed by Wm. Vanderson (Box 1, Folder 2)
- 1762-1775
  - 3 receipts to Jacob van Schaick - 1762, 1765, 1766 - from Tho. Franklin, John McCregs, Jacob G. Lansingh (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1 List of goods received by J. Roorback from Jacob van Schaick - 1763 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1 Letter to Jacob van Schaick, Albany - 1762 - from P. Livingston, N. Y. - acknowledges receipt of power of attorney for collection of a bill (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 4 Letters to Jacob van Schaick, Albany
    - 1771 - from Thomas Harris, London - Feb. 9 - sends bill of lading for gunpowder which is not on boat due to an accident -"this is an article which by law is not to be kept in any particular quantity near the city, and is always kept ready on boats about 10 or 15 miles down the river to put on board when the vessel comes down" by some neglect, the powder missed the boat. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1771 - from Thomas Harris - Mar. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1771 - from Pink van der Hayden, London - speaks of the death of Thomas Harris - "after a short illness of a violent fever" (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1775 - copy of a letter from John Blackburn, London - quotes prices of wheat, flour. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1 Letter to Jacob van Schaick, Albany 1769 - from his nephew, G. van Schaick. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 1780-1784
  - 3 Letters to Jacob van Schaick, Albany
    - 1780 - from Peter Livingston, complaining of too high rates charged by van Schaick for storing pearl ash bought by Livingston - answer on same letter stating that the bill was a mistake and giving proper rate. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1780 - from Livingston, acknowledging receipt of new bill which is acceptable (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1783 - from Ph. Schuyler, N. Y. - says his son will be "liberated immediately" - and he has instructed one of "the general's aides de camp to advance your son 5 or 6 dollars and recommend him to come up home" (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1 Receipt - 1784 - to Jacob van Schaick to Corns. Ray. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Will of Anthony van Schaick, Albany, 1781 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 2 Land Deeds
    - 1784 - Christina van Schaick, Isle Cohoes, Albany Co., and Stephen Wyle, Half Moon, rental of property - 6 pounds a year for 50 years (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1785 - Maria van Schaick, Albany and Conrad Ruby of Colony of Renselaerwyck - rental of property, 40 shillings a year for 15 years (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 1786-1799
  - 3 Receipts
    - To Jacob van Schaick from Wendell's Hat Manufactory - 1786 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1798 - Aaron Dericklane to Christina van Schaick (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1799 - Mary Stymets from Mrs. Van Schagh (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 4 Accounts and receipts
    - 1788 - Shoemakers account of Mrs. van Schaick (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1786 - Jacob Pruyer - Dutch (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1798 - Dr. Henry to Mr. van Scoyke (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1798-1799 - Anna van Schaick from Aaron Dericklane (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Last will and testament of Goose van Schaick (1736-1789) - 1786 - fair copy. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1 Deed, sale of a negro woman, about 30 - Oct. 11, 1787 - James Bleecker to Jacob van Schaick - 75 pounds. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 1800-1819
  - 5 Deeds
    - 1806 - James Cameron and Gerrit van Schaick, Albany - $480. 00 -mortgage on property to be paid before 1811 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1809 - Lewis Fortner and James McElheeny, Cayuga Co. - $450.00 -150 acres (autograph of Derick Sutfin, one of founders of first Pres. Church, Dryden) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1811 - Gerrit W. van Schaick and Peter Wendover (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1813 - Anna van Schaick, Albany Co. and Peter Steenbergh, Saratoga Co. - rental, 35 years - $12.50 year (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1819 - Deed in partition - Gerrit Peebles and Christina, Gerard, Anthony, Henry, Wessel van Schaick (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 4 Accounts
    - 1800 - Anna van Schaick with Aaron Dericklane (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1804 - Maria van Schaick with John van Schaick (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1818 - Henry van Schaick to the estate of Gerrit van Schaick, deceased. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Liquidated book account between heirs of Anna van Schaick (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 2 Receipts - 1806 Last will and testament of Christina van Schaick - 1808 Map of one square in Fox street, by J. Barclay - 1802 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- 1820-1846
  - 1 Bill of sale - 1820 - Daniel van Leukam, Anthony van Leukam to John van Leukam, Saratoga Co. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1 Bill and receipt - 1821-1822 - Dr. Eansworth - 1 account of Dr. Peter Pausevoock with certain tenants (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1 Bill in account with Gerrit Peebles - 1826 - 1828 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1 Account - 1822 - Gerard van Schaick to the estate of Anthony van Schaick (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1 Receipt - 1822 - Henry van Schaick to Nicholas Trumpbour (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 2 Letters - 1822 - Thos. Gardner, Great Limbaugh, to Gerard van Schaick, Waterford (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1821 - Gerard van Schaick, Waterford to Henry van Schaick (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - List of contracts and unsold lands of Gerrit van Schaick, deceased, 1823 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 2 Specifications for a "double dwelling house, 39 ft., 10 inches front and rear, divided into two stories" - 1826 - for Henry van Schaick, Albany, N. Y. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1 Receipt - 1846 - Moses Woodaux to W. W. Baldwin (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Undated
  - 1 Bill of damages sustained by Henry van Schaick "by means of the State dam below Lansingburgh in town of Watervliet" (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Inventory of goods in possession of Lucinda van Schaick (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1 list of lots (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1 Plan of Oswego (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 3 letters, Albany, N.Y.
    - 1 to Jacob van Schaick from Hendrick Cuyler (in Dutch) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1 to Jacob van Schaick from J. N. Bleecker (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1 from Matthew Harrison to Mrs. van Schaick about boarding her daughter, Christina (Box 1, Folder 8)